Alright, stepped out of the office for a little bit, new surroundings, and let's take this
opportunity for a bit of a recap. ZFS is a physical file system like HFS. It's
not an HFS replacement, it's complementary. However, note that HFS has
been functionally stabilized since ZOS version 1.6 and new enhancements are only
brought in the context of ZFS. A ZFS aggregate is a data set that contains
the ZFS file system. The aggregate is a VSAM linear data set or VSAM LDS and is
a container that can contain one or more ZFS file systems. The name of the aggregate
is the same as the VSAM LDS name. A ZFS aggregate that contains only a single
ZFS file system can be defined and is called a compatibility mode aggregate.
Compatibility mode aggregates are more like HFS. Aggregates that contain
multiple file systems are called multi-file system aggregates and this
type of aggregate is no longer supported. Okay, so you can choose whether each file
system is to be an HFS or a ZFS on the data set attributes panel or with the
change DSN type command. The root file system can also be a ZFS. VSAM files and
ZFSs are not quite as easy to work with as HFSs. For example, you can't
uncatalog them and renaming them is a bit more difficult. Although the HFS
data set does not have to be SMS managed it is still highly recommended.
Multivolume HFS data sets are only supported as SMS managed that is you
cannot have multivolume non-SMS managed data sets. Finally, you do not
need to migrate all of your file systems to ZFS all at once. HFS and ZFS
can coexist and you can migrate some or all at your own pace. Previously you could
only migrate mounted HFS file systems to ZFS but now with ZOS 2.1 you can use
the BPXWMIGF command to migrate mounted HFS file systems to ZFS. If you
expect a file system to grow larger than 4 gigabytes and it's not SMS
managed with extended addressability you'll need to copy it to an SMS
managed ZFS data set with a data class that includes extended addressability. If
a ZFS aggregate is to be larger than 4 gigabytes it must be SMS managed with a
data class that includes extended addressability. However, there can be
non-SMS managed VSAM linear data sets that are larger than 4 gigabytes with
the extended addressability feature. Hierarchical file system data sets have
partitioned organization, have the same structure as a PDSE and might or might
not be SMS managed. To create an HFS data set specify the usual DD statement
parameters which are necessary to create any ZOS data set. One way of using a file
in the hierarchical file system is to refer to it by JCL. The following
changes have been made to support hierarchical files. First off, DSN type
equals HFS or pipe. Specify HFS to create a hierarchical file system data set or
pipe to specify a named pipe. Path identifies a file in the hierarchical
file system. The JCL support allows a path name to be up to 255 characters
long including the slashes. If the path name contains lower case letters the
name must be enclosed by single quotes. Path DISP specifies the disposition of a
hierarchical file after normal or abnormal end. It can be keep or delete.
Path mode specifies the file access attributes when the file specified in the
path parameter is created. The file access attributes define who has access
to read, write or execute the file. And path ops specifies the access and
status for a file. There are two file option groups, the access group and the
status group. Now this shows an example of how to allocate an HFS data set for
the root file system. The important JCL keyword here is DSN type equals HFS.
Note that an HFS can be either SMS or non-SMS managed but must be cataloged for
them out to succeed. An alternative to using JCL would be to use the TSO
allocate command. The IOE AG FMT utility is used to format an existing VSAM LDS
as a ZFS aggregate. All ZFS aggregates must be formatted before use including
HFS compatibility mode aggregates. IOE AG FMT does not require the ZFS physical
file system to be active on the system. Here is an example of a job to create
and format a compatibility mode aggregate. It's a two-step job. The first
step creates the aggregate and the second step formats it. Since it's a
compatibility mode aggregate, the second step also creates a file system with
the same name as the VSAM LDS cluster entry name and sets the quota to the
size of the aggregate. Just briefly, ZOS 2.1 supports a new directory format V5
using an extensible hashing system. You can optionally migrate to a new version
1.5 file system. There are multiple means to convert to the new file system.
There are new parameters and commands in support of ZFS extended directories. A V5
directory can only exist in a V1.5 aggregate. Version 1.5 aggregates
support extended V5 directories. Extended V5 directories can support larger
directories, store names more efficiently than V4 directories, and reclaim space
when names are removed. A V5 directory cannot be created unless a file system
is V5. A file system can only be converted to V5 or created as V5 by
using either the IOE FSUTL convert format or ZFS ADM convert. This JCL
example shows a program in a ZOS data set being relinked to reside in the
hierarchical file system. PATH defines the path name of the directory where the
program payroll resides when linked edited. The path name is in lowercase
letters and therefore enclosed by single quotes. We have some PATH option
options. OWR only specifies the file will be opened. For write, Ocreate
specifies that if the file doesn't exist it's created and if it is
existing it is reused and OTR UNC specifies that the file length will be
truncated to zero if the file already exists. And for PATH mode SIRWXU
specifies that the file owner has read, write and execute permission. SIRWXG
specifies that the file group has read, write and execute permission and SIRWXO
specifies that all other users have read, write and execute permission. Next
we're going to talk about how to get some stuff done in your UNIX
environment using the iShell and directory list utility.